Herbert Kline Papers
Herbert Kline Papers
1919-1971
Kline, Herbert.
4.5 linear ft.
Correspondence, clippings, writings, memorabilia, scrapbooks of the documentary film maker who chronicled political crises in Europe in the 1930s and 1940s.
2703495
Biographical History
Herbert Kline (1910-1999) was an American documentary film maker who chronicled political crises in Europe in the 1930s and 1940s.
Herbert Kline was born in Davenport, Iowa. As a young man he edited Chicago's liberal New Theater magazine and joined the Photo League, a group of politically progressive photojournalists and documentarists. His work documented a wide range of issues in Europe and Central America, including the Spanish Civil War ( Heart of Spain, 1937; Return to Life, 1938), the rise of Hitler and fascism ( Crisis, 1938; Lights Out in Europe, 1939; My Father's House, 1941), and peasant life in Mexico ( The Forgotten Village, 1941). His sentiments earned him a place on the House Un-American Affairs Committee blacklist and between 1949 and 1970 he produced only one film, an adaptation of Jack London's short story "The Mexican" entitled The Fighter. His Walls of Fire (1971), about Mexican artists Diego Rivera and David Alfaro, was nominated for an Academy Award and won a Golden Globe for best documentary film.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Herbert Kline Papers contains correspondence subject files, memorabilia, printed material, writings, and videotapes.
Correspondence-subject files primarily relate to Kline's film projects, though there is also correspondence with some individuals (John Steinbeck, Cornell Wilde). Many of the film projects were based on novels or stories by other authors (for example, The Fighter was based on a short story by Jack London); where known, original authors are given in parentheses after the film title. Not all projects came to fruition.
Memorabilia consists of three scrapbooks and assorted miscellaneous items. The scrapbook postcards is particularly interesting, containing both progressive and communist graphic images as well as postcards issues by the Spanish ministry of propaganda. Although the postcards have been removed from their scrapbook pages they remain in original order. The other two scrapbooks consist almost entirely of clippings related to Kline's films.
The bulk of Printed material is clippings related to Kline's films. There are also a few catalogs and advertisements for independent, documentary, or educational films and a few miscellaneous items.
Videos contains four tapes comprising two of Kline's later works, one on acting and one on modern art.
Writings includes articles, notes and partial manuscript of Kline's autobiography which he had called Misadventures of a Film Gypsy, an outline, a poem, several screenplays, a children's story written for his daughter Elissa, and two plays by playwright and director Noel Langley (1911-1980).
Arrangement of the Collection
All series are arranged in alphabetical order.
Because the majority of clippings were oversize, as well as in brittle and yellowed condition, they have been filed separately under Clippings rather than with the movie to which they pertain. Researchers should review the entire finding aid to ensure locating all relevant material.
Separated Material
Several issues of Doho, a liberal newspaper created by and for "nisei" or second-generation Japanese Americans, were sent to Rare Books for cataloging (Sep 2009). Please refer to to locate these items.
Subject and Genre Headings
Kline, Herbert.; Documentary films.; War films.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Motion pictures and the war.; Czechoslovakia -- History -- 1918-1938.; Europe, Eastern -- History -- 20th century.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Motion pictures and the war.; Correspondence.; Clippings (information artifacts); Photographs.; Poems.; Screenplays.; Videotapes.; Motion picture producers and directors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Originals of two of the three scrapbooks are restricted due to fragile condition and may not be opened without special permission. Photocopies are provided in the collection. Access to beta tapes requires advance notice to produce working copy.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Elissa Kline, 2009.
Inventory
- Correspondence-subject files
  - Adam and Eve, See Franklyn costs
  - Blaze of Glory, 1966; summary only (Box 1)
  - Bolivar, 1959-1961; includes photographs (Box 1)
  - Crisis, 1939; photographs, program from world premiere at 55th Street Playhouse (Box 1)
  - Danton's Death, See Wilde, Cornell.
  - Dark Wedding (Ramon Sender), 1953 (Box 1)
  - Essex, Harry / "The Walls of Heaven", undated; novella? (Box 1)
  - Family correspondence, 1919; 1963,; undated; most to Josy Kline (wife); one from Elissa Kline (daughter) and one to Kline's siblings (Box 1)
  - The Fighter (Jack London), 1951-1952; undated; includes photographs, clipping of color advertisement, legal documents (Box 1)
  - "Franklyn costs", 1955; material from envelope labeled by Kline as "Franklyn costs for Adam & Eve and English film" (Box 1)
  - Let Me Breathe Thunder (Bill Attaway), 1953 (Box 1)
  - Lights Out in Europe, photographs only (Box 1)
  - The Mexican (Jack London), 1950 (Box 1)
  - Moll Flanders, 1955 (Box 1)
  - My Father's House (Meyer Levin), 1945-1947; includes photographs, double-page spread advertisement, story outline with earlier title, "The Survivors"; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - On Love and Terror, 1967; includes photocopy of clipping from The Jerusalem Post (Box 1)
  - Photographs
    - "Wall photos", photographs from an envelope so labeled by Kline (Box 1)
    - Unidentified (Box 1)
      See also specific movie titles, several have photographs
  - Song of Ruth (Irving Feinman), 1960-1962; includes a few clippings (Box 1)
  - Spain, Spanish hospitals, 1937; letters of introduction, expenses, etc. relating to a public relations film on Spanish hospitals (Box 1)
  - Sparks Fly Upward (Oliver La Farge), 1953 (Box 2)
  - Star Rover (Jack London), 1953 (Box 2)
  - Steinbeck, John, 1940; 1952; See also Clippings: The Forgotten Village (Box 2)
  - The Survivors, See My Father's House
  - Sword of Galilee, 1961; includes proposed casting (Box 2)
  - The Thief and the Cross, 1959; also mentions film on Barabbas (Box 2)
  - Thieves' Market, photos only (Box 2)
  - Tia Juana Miracle (Zeilicovici), 1962 (Box 2)
  - A Time to Love, See On Love and Terror
  - Walls of Fire, 1971; advertisement, partial transcript of voice-overs (Box 2)
  - Wilde, Cornell, 1961 (Box 2)
  - The Yankee, 1952 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1935-1966; undated (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous other (Box 2)
- Memorabilia
  - Scrapbook, postcards, circa 1935-1950?; collection of liberal, leftist, progressive, and/or communist graphic-image postcards from various countries; also includes photographic postcards put out by the Spanish Ministry of Propaganda (Oversize 1)
  - Scrapbooks, miscellaneous, circa 1935-1953; clippings related to Kline's movies; 2 volumes (Oversize 2)
    Box contains both original scrapbooks and complete photocopies. Originals are restricted due to fragile condition and researchers should use the photocopies only.
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Printed material
  - Clippings
    - About Kline, 1955; undated (Box 2)
    - Bolivar, 1960 (Oversize 3)
    - The Cleveland Story / The Kid from Cleveland, 1949 (Oversize 3)
    - Crisis, 1939; includes large double-page spread advertisement / poster (Oversize 3)
    - The Fighter, 1952 (Oversize 3)
    - Forgotten Village, 1941 (Oversize 3)
    - Heart of Spain, 1937? (Oversize 3)
    - Hostages, 1942-1943 (Oversize 3)
    - Lights out in Europe, 1940 (Oversize 3)
    - My Father's House, 1947 (Oversize 3)
    - See What I Mean, 1944 (Oversize 3)
    - Miscellaneous, subjects include Elia Kazan's statement on his Communist Party membership, Palestine, Spanish Civil War, World War II (Oversize 4)
  - Film sources
    - Catalogs (Box 2)
    - Individual films, fliers, ads, reviews, etc. (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Videos
  - The Challenge of Modern Art, 2 Betamax tapes (Box 5)
  - Acting: Lee Strasberg and the Actors Studio, 2 Betamax tapes (Box 5)
- Writings
  - Articles
    - "Behind Loyalist Lines," New York Times, 18 Apr 1937 (Box 2)
    - "Films Without Make-Believe," Magazine of Art, Feb 1942 (Box 2)
  - Autobiography
    - "Misadventures of a Film Gypsy", notes, original photographs, heavily annotated photocopies of articles and photographs, partial draft manuscript (starts with p. 115); 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Outlines
    - "See What I Mean?" (Box 3)
  - Poems
    - Untitled, on the sinking of the HMS Thetis, unattributed; may or may not be by Kline (Box 3)
  - Screenplays
    - Bolivar, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Calypsoland (with Bill Attaway) (Box 3)
    - The Hill of Hope (with Aben Kandel) (Box 3)
    - Love, Hate and Greed (Box 3)
    - A Love Story (Box 3)
    - Nicaragua (with Stephen Kandel) (Box 3)
    - The Sun and the Sword (with Bill Attaway) (Box 3)
  - Stories
    - Nighwatch, "a story by Daddy...for Ethan and Elissa" (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Unidentified fragments (Box 4)
  - By others
    - Langley, Noel / The Ambush of Young Days, play (Box 4)
    - Langley, Noel / The Big Squeeze, play (Box 4)